I'm here to talk about
انا هنا لاتحدث عن
the wonder and the mystery
التساؤل والغموض
of conscious minds.
في العقول الواعية
The wonder is about the fact
التساؤل في الحقيقة
that we all woke up this morning
اننا جميعا قد استيقظنا في هذا الصباح
and we had with it
ومعنا كذلك
the amazing return of our conscious mind.
عودة عقلنا الواعي الرائع
We recovered minds with a complete sense of self
استعدنا عقولنا مع كامل شعورنا بالذات
and a complete sense of our own existence,
والشعور الكامل بوجودنا الشخصي
yet we hardly ever pause to consider this wonder.
ومع ذلك فإننا بالكاد نقف للنظر في هذا التساؤل
We should, in fact,
في الحقيقة, يستوجب علينا ذلك
because without having this possibility of conscious minds,
لأنه بدون وجود هذا الاحتمال من عقول واعية
we would have no knowledge whatsoever
لن يكون لدينا اي علم على الاطلاق
about our humanity;
حول إنسانيتنا
we would have no knowledge whatsoever about the world.
لن يكون لدينا اي علم على الاطلاق عن العالم
We would have no pains, but also no joys.
لن يكون لدينا آلام, ولا افراح
We would have no access to love
لن نحصل على الحب
or to the ability to create.
او القدرة على الخلق
And of course, Scott Fitzgerald said famously
وطبعا, قال سكوت فيتزجيرالد كما هو معروف
that "he who invented consciousness
ان "الذي اخترع الوعي
would have a lot to be blamed for."
يتحمل مسؤولية الكثير"
But he also forgot
لكنه نسي ايضا
that without consciousness,
انه بدون الوعي
he would have no access to true happiness
لن يحصل على السعادة الحقيقية
and even the possibility of transcendence.
وحتى في إمكانية التعالي
So much for the wonder, now for the mystery.
هنالك الكثير للتساؤل, والان للغموض
This is a mystery
هذا غموض
that has really been extremely hard to elucidate.
يصعب فعلا توضيحه
All the way back into early philosophy
رجوعا الى بدايات الفلسفة
and certainly throughout the history of neuroscience,
وبالتأكيد طوال تاريخ علم الأعصاب,
this has been one mystery
كان هذا لغزا
that has always resisted elucidation,
صعب دائما توضيحه
has got major controversies.
احدث جدلا كبيرا
And there are actually many people
وهناك العديد من الناس فعلا
that think we should not even touch it;
تعتقد انه يجب ان لا نلتمسه حتى,
we should just leave it alone, it's not to be solved.
ينبغي علينا تركه, فلسنا بحاجة الى حله
I don't believe that,
انا لا اؤمن بذلك,
and I think the situation is changing.
و اظن ان الوضع يتغير.
It would be ridiculous to claim
من السخف الادعاء
that we know how we make consciousness
أننا نعرف كيفية صنع الوعي
in our brains,
في عقولنا,
but we certainly can begin
ولكن بالتأكيد يمكننا أن نبدأ
to approach the question,
للتعامل مع المسألة,
and we can begin to see the shape of a solution.
ويمكننا أن نبدأ في رؤية شكل للحل
And one more wonder to celebrate
وتساؤل اخر للاعلان عنه
is the fact that we have imaging technologies
هو حقيقة ان لدينا تقنيات التصوير
that now allow us to go inside the human brain
التي تمكننا من الدخول الى عقل الانسان
and be able to do, for example,
والتمكن من, على سبيل المثال
what you're seeing right now.
ما ترونه الان
These are images that come from Hanna Damasio's lab,
هذه صور اتت من مختبر هانا داماسيو
and which show you, in a living brain,
والتي تعرض لكم, داخل الدماغ الحي
the reconstruction of that brain.
إعادة بناء هذا الدماغ
And this is a person who is alive.
وهذا الانسان الحي
This is not a person
هذا ليس شخصا
that is being studied at autopsy.
تتم دراسته تشريحيا
And even more --
و اكثر من ذلك --
and this is something that one can be really amazed about --
وهذا شيء يمكن أن يثير الدهشة --
is what I'm going to show you next,
هذا الذي ساريكم اياه بعده,
which is going underneath the surface of the brain
الذي يجري تحت سطح الدماغ
and actually looking in the living brain
وحقيقةً يبحث داخل المخ الحي
at real connections, real pathways.
في اتصالات حقيقية ومسارات حقيقية.
So all of those colored lines
لذلك كل هذه الخطوط الملونة
correspond to bunches of axons,
تتوافق مع باقات من المحاوير,
the fibers that join cell bodies
الالياف التي تربط الهيئات الخلية
to synapses.
الى المشابك
And I'm sorry to disappoint you, they don't come in color.
واعتذر لتخييب ظنكم, لكنها لا تاتي ملونة
But at any rate, they are there.
ولكن على اية حال, فهي موجودة
The colors are codes for the direction,
الالوان ترمز للاتجاه
from whether it is back to front
سواء كانت من الخلف إلى الأمام
or vice versa.
او عكس ذلك
At any rate, what is consciousness?
على أية حال، ما هو الوعي؟
What is a conscious mind?
ما هو العقل الواعي؟
And we could take a very simple view
ويمكن اتخاذ وجهة نظر بسيطة جدا
and say, well, it is that which we lose
ونقول، حسنا ، انه هو ذلك الذي نفتقده
when we fall into deep sleep without dreams,
عندما نقع في النوم العميق دون أحلام
or when we go under anesthesia,
أو عندما نكون تحت تأثير التخدير،
and it is what we regain
وهو ما نستعيده
when we recover from sleep
عندما نستيقظ من النوم
or from anesthesia.
او من التخدير.
But what is exactly that stuff that we lose under anesthesia,
ولكن ما هي بالضبط الاشياء التي نفقدها تحت تأثير التخدير،
or when we are in deep, dreamless sleep?
او عندما نمكث في نوم عميق بلا احلام
Well first of all,
حسنا, اول شيئ
it is a mind,
هو العقل
which is a flow of mental images.
وهو مسار الصور الذهنية
And of course consider images
وطبعا ننظر الى صور
that can be sensory patterns,
بامكانها ان تكون انماط حسية,
visual, such as you're having right now
مرئية, مثل التي تعيشها الان
in relation to the stage and me,
بالنسبة إلى المسرح ولي,
or auditory images,
أو الصور السمعية،
as you are having now in relation to my words.
كما تعيشونها الان فيما يتعلق بكلامي.
That flow of mental images
هذا التدفق من الصور الذهنية
is mind.
هو العقل
But there is something else
ولكن هنالك شيئ أخر
that we are all experiencing in this room.
نشهده الان في هذه القاعة
We are not passive exhibitors
لسنا عوارض سلبية
of visual or auditory
للسمعية او البصرية
or tactile images.
أو الصور المسية.
We have selves.
لدينا انفس.
We have a Me
ولدينا "انا"
that is automatically present
الحاضرة تلقائيا
in our minds right now.
في اذهاننا الان
We own our minds.
نحن نمتلك عقولنا
And we have a sense that it's everyone of us
ولدينا شعور بأن كل واحد منا
that is experiencing this --
يحس هذا الشيئ
not the person who is sitting next to you.
ليس الشخص الذي يجلس إلى جانبك.
So in order to have a conscious mind,
لذلك ليكون لديك عقل واعي,
you have a self within the conscious mind.
لديك نفس داخل العقل الواعي
So a conscious mind is a mind with a self in it.
فالعقل الواعي هو عقل به نفس في داخله.
The self introduces the subjective perspective in the mind,
النفس تقدم المنظور الشخصي في العقل،
and we are only fully conscious
ونحن فقط على وعي تام
when self comes to mind.
عنما يتبادر الذات الى الذهن.
So what we need to know to even address this mystery
فما نحن في حاجة الى معرفته لمعالجة هذا الغموض
is, number one, how are minds are put together in the brain,
هو, اول شيئ كيف وضعت العقول معا في الدماغ
and, number two, how selves are constructed.
و الثاني, كيف يتم بناء النفس.
Now the first part, the first problem,
الان الجزء الاول, المشكلة الاولى,
is relatively easy -- it's not easy at all --
نسبيا سهلة -- هي ليست سهلة على الاطلاق
but it is something that has been approached gradually in neuroscience.
ولكنه أمر قد تم تناوله تدريجيا في علم الأعصاب
And it's quite clear that, in order to make minds,
والواضح تماما أنه لصنع العقول،
we need to construct neural maps.
نحن بحاجة إلى بناء الخرائط العصبية.
So imagine a grid, like the one I'm showing you right now,
لذلك تخيل شبكة. مثل التي اعرضها لكم الان
and now imagine, within that grid,
وتخيل الآن ، داخل تلك الشبكة,
that two-dimensional sheet,
ورقتين ثنائيتي الأبعاد،
imagine neurons.
تخيل الخلايا العصبية
And picture, if you will,
وتخيل, إذا صح تعبيري،
a billboard, a digital billboard,
لوحة، لوحة رقمية،
where you have elements
حيث لديك عناصر
that can be either lit or not.
يمكن أن تكون مضاءة أو لا.
And depending on how you create the pattern
واعتمادا على كيفية إنشائك للنموذج
of lighting or not lighting,
للاضائة او عدم اضائة,
the digital elements,
العناصر الرقمية،
or, for that matter, the neurons in the sheet,
أو، في هذه الحالة، الخلايا العصبية في الورقة،
you're going to be able to construct a map.
ستكون قادر على بناء خريطة.
This, of course, is a visual map that I'm showing you,
هذه، طبعاً ، عبارة عن خريطة بصرية أعرضها عليكم،
but this applies to any kind of map --
ولكن هذا ينطبق على أي نوع من الخرائط --
auditory, for example, in relation to sound frequencies,
السمعية، على سبيل المثال، فيما يتعلق بالترددات الصوتية،
or to the maps that we construct with our skin
أو على الخرائط التي نبنيها ببشرتنا
in relation to an object that we palpate.
بالنسبة للجسم الذي نفحصه.
Now to bring home the point
الان لإعادة النقطة
of how close it is --
عن كيفما هي قريبة
the relationship between the grid of neurons
العلاقة ما بين شبكة الخلايا العصبية
and the topographical arrangement
والترتيب الطوبوغرافي
of the activity of the neurons
لنشاط الخلايا العصبية
and our mental experience --
وتجربتنا العقلية --
I'm going to tell you a personal story.
سأشارككم بقصة شخصية.
So if I cover my left eye --
فان غطيت عيني اليسرى --
I'm talking about me personally, not all of you --
فانا اتحدث عن نفسي شخصيا, وليس عنكم
if I cover my left eye,
فان غطيت عيني اليسرى,
I look at the grid -- pretty much like the one I'm showing you.
انا انظر الى الشبكة -- الى حد كبير تشبه التي امامكم
Everything is nice and fine and perpendicular.
كل شيء جميل وجيد وعمودي
But sometime ago, I discovered
ولكن فيما مضى, اكتشفت
that if I cover my left eye,
انني اذا غطيت عيني اليسرى,
instead what I get is this.
بدلا من ذلك, احصل على هذا
I look at the grid and I see a warping
أنا أنظر إلى الشبكة وأرى تشويه
at the edge of my central-left field.
على حافة الحقل الوسطي-اليساري
Very odd -- I've analyzed this for a while.
غريب جدا-- لقد حلّلت هذا لبعض الوقت
But sometime ago,
ولكن منذ فترة,
through the help of an opthamologist colleague of mine,
من خلال مساعدة من زميل لي طبيب العيون،
Carmen Puliafito,
كارمن بوليافيتو
who developed a laser scanner of the retina,
الذي طور ماسح ليزر لشبكية العين
I found out the the following.
وجدت التالي
If I scan my retina
اذا انا فحصت شبكية عيني
through the horizontal plane that you see there in the little corner,
من خلال المستوى الأفقي الذي ترونه هناك في الزاوية الصغيرة،
what I get is the following.
ما اتحصل عليه هو ما يلي
On the right side, my retina is perfectly symmetrical.
على الجانب الأيمن، شبكية العين لدي متماثلة تماما.
You see the going down towards the fovea
ترون النزول نحو الفوفيا
where the optic nerve begins.
حيث تبدأ العصبة البصرية
But on my left retina there is a bump,
ولكن على شبكية العين اليسرى هناك عثرة،
which is marked there by the red arrow.
عُلمت بالسهم الاحمر
And it corresponds to a little cyst
وهي تشبه كيسة صغيرة
that is located below.
واقعة بالاسفل.
And that is exactly what causes
وهذا هو بالضبط ما يسبب
the warping of my visual image.
تشويه صورتي المرئية
So just think of this:
فقط فكر في هذا:
you have a grid of neurons,
لديكم شبكة من الخلايا العصبية،
and now you have a plane mechanical change
والآن لديكم تغيير في المستوى الميكانيكي
in the position of the grid,
في وضع الشبكة
and you get a warping of your mental experience.
وتحصل على تشويه في تجربتك العقلية.
So this is how close
لذلك هذا هو مدى قرب
your mental experience
تجربتك العقلية
and the activity of the neurons in the retina,
ونشاط الخلايا العصبية في شبكية العين،
which is a part of the brain located in the eyeball,
وهي جزء من الدماغ يقع في مقلة العين،
or, for that matter, a sheet of visual cortex.
أو، في هذه الحالة، ورقة من القشرة البصرية
So from the retina
لذا من الشبكية
you go onto visual cortex.
تذهب على القشرة البصرية.
And of course, the brain adds on
وبطبيعة الحال ، يضيف الدماغ
a lot of information
الكثير من المعلومات
to what is going on
الى ما يحدث
in the signals that come from the retina.
من خلال الاشارات التي تاتي الى شبكية العين
And in that image there,
و في تلك الصورة هنالك,
you see a variety of islands
ترى مجموعة من الجزر
of what I call image-making regions in the brain.
ما اسميه منطقة صنع الصور في الدماغ
You have the green for example,
لديكم الاخضر على سبيل المثال,
that corresponds to tactile information,
الذي يتطابق مع المعلومات اللمسية
or the blue that corresponds to auditory information.
او الازرق الذي يطابق المعلومات السمعية
And something else that happens
وشيئ آخر يحدث
is that those image-making regions
هو ان تلك المناطق التي تصنع الصور
where you have the plotting
حيثما يكون لديك الرسم
of all these neural maps,
ما بين كل هذه الخرائط العصبية
can then provide signals
بامكانها اعطاء اشارات
to this ocean of purple that you see around,
الى هذا المحيط الارجواني الذي تراه حولك
which is the association cortex,
وهو القشرة الترابطية
where you can make records of what went on
حيث يمكنك صنع سجل عن ما حدث
in those islands of image-making.
في جزر صناعة الصور
And the great beauty
و الجميل جدا
is that you can then go from memory,
هو أنك بامكامنك أن تذهب بعد ذلك من الذاكرة
out of those association cortices,
من هذه القشرات الترابطية,
and produce back images
واعادة صنع الصور
in the very same regions that have perception.
في نفس منطقة القدرة على الفهم
So think about how wonderfully convenient and lazy
لذلك فكر حول كيفية هو رائع و مريح و كسول
the brain is.
هو الدماغ
So it provides certain areas
فهو يوفر بعض المناطق
for perception and image-making.
للتصور و التصوير
And those are exactly the same
وهذه بالضبط هي
that are going to be used for image-making
التي ستستخدم للتصوير
when we recall information.
عندما نسترجع المعلومات
So far the mystery of the conscious mind
حتى الان لغز العقل الواعي
is diminishing a little bit
يتناقص بعض الشيئ
because we have a general sense
لأن لدينا بالمعنى العام
of how we make these images.
عن كيفية صنع هذه الصور
But what about the self?
ولكن ماذا عن النفس؟
The self is really the elusive problem.
النفس هي فعلا المشكلة المراوغة
And for a long time,
ولفترة طويلة,
people did not even want to touch it,
لم يرد الناس يريدون حتى لمسها،
because they'd say,
لانهم كانوا يقولون,
"How can you have this reference point, this stability,
"كيف بامكانك الحصول على هذه النقطة المرجعية، وهذا الاستقرار،
that is required to maintain
ما هو مطلوب للحفاظ على
the continuity of selves day after day?"
استمرارية أنفسنا يوما بعد يوم؟ "
And I thought about a solution to this problem.
وفكرت في حل لهذه المشكلة
It's the following.
هو التالي
We generate brain maps
ان نولد خرائط الدماغ
of the body's interior
لداخلية الجسم
and use them as the reference for all other maps.
واستخدامها كمرجع لكل الخرائط
So let me tell you just a little bit about how I came to this.
دعوني احدثكم قليلا عن كيف توصلت الى هذا
I came to this because,
وصلت الى هذا لان,
if you're going to have a reference that we know as self --
اذا كان لديك مرجع يعرف بالنفس
the Me, the I
شخصي, او انا
in our own processing --
في نشئتنا الشخصية
we need to have something that is stable,
نحن في حاجة الى شيئ مسقر
something that does not deviate much
شيئ يكون لا ينحرف كثيرا
from day to day.
من يوم الى اخر
Well it so happens that we have a singular body.
حسنا حدث وان لدينا جسم فردي.
We have one body, not two, not three.
نملك جسم واحد, وليس اثنان, او ثلاثة.
And so that is a beginning.
وتلك هي البداية.
There is just one reference point, which is the body.
هنالك نقطة مرجع واحدة, و هي الجسد.
But then, of course, the body has many parts,
ولكن, طبعا, الجسد له اعضاء كثيرة,
and things grow at different rates,
والأشياء تنمو بمعدلات مختلفة,
and they have different sizes and different people;
ولديها احجام مختلفة و اناس مختلفة;
however, not so with the interior.
مع ذلك, هذا لا ينطبق على الداخل
The things that have to do
الأشياء التي لها علاقة
with what is known as our internal milieu --
مع ما هو معروف لدينا بالوسط الداخلي --
for example, the whole management
مثلاً, جميع الادارة
of the chemistries within our body
الكيمائية داخل اجسامنا
are, in fact, extremely maintained
هي, في الواقع, محافظ عليها للغاية
day after day
يوما بعد يوم
for one very good reason.
لسبب واحد وجيه.
If you deviate too much
اذا انحرفت كثيرا
in the parameters
في المعايير
that are close to the midline
المتقاربة من خط الوسط
of that life-permitting survival range,
لنطاق البقاء السامح للحياة,
you go into disease or death.
تصاب بالمرض او الموت
So we have an in-built system
لذلك لدينا نظام مدمج
within our own lives
داخل حياتنا
that ensures some kind of continuity.
يضمن شيئا من الاستمرارية.
I like to call it an almost infinite sameness from day to day.
احب تسميته شبه تماثل لا نهائي من يوم لاخر.
Because if you don't have that sameness, physiologically,
لأنه إذا ليس لديك هذا التشابه، من الناحية الفسيولوجية،
you're going to be sick or you're going to die.
ستصاب بالمرض او قد تموت
So that's one more element for this continuity.
لذا هذا احد عناصر الاستمرارية
And the final thing
واخر شيئ
is that there is a very tight coupling
هو ان هنالك اتصال ضيق جدا
between the regulation of our body within the brain
مابين تنظيم الجسم في الدماغ
and the body itself,
والجسم نفسه،
unlike any other coupling.
بخلاف اي اتصال اخر
So for example, I'm making images of you,
فعلى سبيل المثال, اذا التقط صور لكم,
but there's no physiological bond
لكن ليس هناك رابطة الفسيولوجية
between the images I have of you as an audience
ما بين صوري لكم كجمهور
and my brain.
و دماغي
However, there is a close, permanently maintained bond
ومع ذلك ، هناك علاقة وثيقة, محافظ على ارتباطها بشكل دائم
between the body regulating parts of my brain
بين أجزاء الجسم التي تنظم دماغي
and my own body.
وجسدي.
So here's how it looks. Look at the region there.
هكذا يبدوا شكله. انظروا الى تلك المنطقة.
There is the brain stem in between the cerebral cortex
هناك في جذع الدماغ بين القشرة الدماغية
and the spinal cord.
والحبل الشوكي
And it is within that region
وهو داخل تلك المنطقة
that I'm going to highlight now
التي ساسلط عليه الضوء الان
that we have this housing
ان لدينا هذا المسكن
of all the life-regulation devices
من جميع الادوات المنظمة للحياة
of the body.
للجسد.
This is so specific that, for example,
هذا دقيق جدا, على سبيل المثال
if you look at the part that is covered in red
اذا نظرت الى الجزء المغطى بالاحمر
in the upper part of the brain stem,
في الجزء العلوي لجذع الدماغ,
if you damage that as a result of a stroke, for example,
اذا عرضته للضرر بسبب سكته دماغية, على سبيل المثال
what you get is coma
تصاب بالغيبوبة
or vegetative state,
او حالة اغماء,
which is a state, of course,
وهي حالة, طبعا,
in which your mind disappears,
تفقدك عقلك
your consciousness disappears.
وتفقد وعيك
What happens then actually
ما يحدث بعدها, في الواقع
is that you lose the grounding of the self,
هو انك ستفقد اساس النفس,
you have no longer access to any feeling of your own existence,
لن يكون لديك بعدها شعور بوجودك,
and, in fact, there can be images going on,
وحقيقة, قد يكون هناك صور متحركة,
being formed in the cerebral cortex,
يتم تشكيلها في القشرة الدماغية،
except you don't know they're there.
إلا انك لا تدري انها موجودة.
You have, in effect, lost consciousness
لديك ، في الواقع ، فقدان للوعي
when you have damage to that red section of the brain stem.
عندما تصيبه بالضرر الى ان يصل تلك المنطقة الحمراء من جذع الدماغ.
But if you consider the green part of the brain stem,
ولكن اذا نظرتم للجزء الاخضر من جذع الدماغ
nothing like that happens.
لن يحدث شيئ من هذا القبيل.
It is that specific.
هكذا هو محدد.
So in that green component of the brain stem,
ففي هذا العنصر الاخضر من جذع الدماغ,
if you damage it, and often it happens,
اذا اصبته بالضرر, و هذا يحدث احيانا
what you get is complete paralysis,
تصيبه بشلل تام,
but your conscious mind is maintained.
ولكن تحتفظ بوعيك العقلي.
You feel, you know, you have a fully conscious mind
تشعرون, كما تعلمون, بان لديكم عقل واعي تماما
that you can report very indirectly.
يمكنكم استرجاعه بطريق غير مباشرة.
This is a horrific condition. You don't want to see it.
هذه حاله مروعة. لن ترد رؤيتها
And people are, in fact, imprisoned
و الناس في الحقيقة, مسجونين,
within their own bodies,
داخل اجسامهم,
but they do have a mind.
لكن لديهم عقول
There was a very interesting film,
كان هناك فيلم مثير جدا للاهتمام،
one of the rare good films done
واحد من الافلام الجيدة النادرة التي عُملت
about a situation like this,
عن حاله كهذه,
by Julian Schnabel some years ago
بواسطة جوليان شنابل منذ بضع سنوات
about a patient that was in that condition.
عن مريض كان في تلك الحالة
So now I'm going to show you a picture.
والان ساريكم صورة.
I promise not to say anything about this,
أعدكم ألا أقول أي شيء حول هذا الموضوع ،
except this is to frighten you.
ما عدا انه سيصيبكم بالرعب
It's just to tell you
هذا فقط ليخبركم
that in that red section of the brain stem,
انه في الجزء الاحمر من جزع الدماغ,
there are, to make it simple,
هنالك, لتسهيل الامر
all those little squares that correspond to modules
كل تلك المربعات الصغيرة وهي نماذج
that actually make brain maps
هي في الحقيقة تصنع خرائط الدماغ
of different aspects of our interior,
لجوانب مختلفة من دواخلنا,
different aspects of our body.
وجوانب مختلفة من اجسامنا.
They are exquisitely topographic
هي طبوغرافية رائعة
and they are exquisitely interconnected
و مترابطة بشكل رائع
in a recursive pattern.
في نمط تكراري.
And it is out of this and out of this tight coupling
وخارجا من هنا وخارج هذا الاتصال الضيق
between the brain stem and the body
ما بين جذع الدماغ و الجسم
that I believe -- and I could be wrong,
اعتقد -- وقد اكون مخطئا
but I don't think I am --
ولكن لا اعتقد انني --
that you generate this mapping of the body
أنك تولد تلك الخرائط من الجسم
that provides the grounding for the self
التي تعطي اسسا للذات
and that comes in the form of feelings --
والتي تأتي في شكل مشاعر
primordial feelings, by the way.
جانبا, مشاعر بدائية.
So what is the picture that we get here?
فما هي الصورة التي نحصل عليها هنا؟
Look at "cerebral cortex," look at "brain stem,"
انظر الى "القشرة الدماغية ،" انظر الى "جذع المخ,"
look at "body,"
انظر الى "الجسم"
and you get the picture of the interconnectivity
و ستحصل على الترابط
in which you have the brain stem providing the grounding for the self
والذي فيه جذع الدماغ معطيا اسسا للذات
in a very tight interconnection with the body.
في ترابط ضيق جدا مع الجسم
And you have the cerebral cortex
ولديك قشرة الدماغ
providing the great spectacle of our minds
معطيا المشاهد العظيمة لعقولنا
with the profusion of images
مع وفرة من الصور
that are, in fact, the contents of our minds
هي, في الحقيقة,محتويات عقولنا
and that we normally pay most attention to,
والتي عادة ما نعطي اكبر قدر من الاهتمام,
as we should, because that's really
كما ينبغي علينا, لانه حقيقة
the film that is rolling in our minds.
الفلم الذي يدور في اذهاننا.
But look at the arrows.
ولكن انظروا الى الاسهم.
They're not there for looks.
هي ليست فقط للنظر اليها.
They're there because there's this very close interaction.
تواجدها هناك لوجود هذا التفاعل الوثيق جدا.
You cannot have a conscious mind
لا يمكن ان يكون لك عقل واعي
if you don't have the interaction
ان لم يكن لديك التفاعل
between cerebral cortex and brain stem.
ما بين قشرة الدماغ وجذع الدماغ.
You cannot have a conscious mind
لا يمكن ان يكون لك عقل واعي
if you don't have the interaction
ان لم يوجد لديك التفاعل
between the brain stem and the body.
مابين جزع الدماغ و الجسم.
Another thing that is interesting
وشيئ اخر مثير للاهتمام
is that the brain stem that we have
ان جذع الدماغ الذي لدينا
is shared with a variety of other species.
مشترك مع اصناف من الكائنات المختلفة الاخرى.
So throughout vertebrates,
بالتالي كل الفقريات
the design of the brain stem is very similar to ours,
تصميم جزع الدماغ مشابه جدا للذي لدينا,
which is one of the reasons why I think
وهو احد الاسباب التي جعلتني افكر
those other species have conscious minds like we do.
ان هذه الاصناف الاخرى لديها عقول واعية كالتي لدينا
Except that they're not as rich as ours,
إلا انها لسيت غنية كما لدينا,
because they don't have a cerebral cortex like we do.
لانها لاتملك قشرة مخ مثلنا.
That's where the difference is.
وهنا يقع الاختلاف.
And I strongly disagree with the idea
وانا اختلف بشده مع فكرة
that consciousness should be considered
انه ينبغي النظر في الوعي
as the great product of the cerebral cortex.
كانه مُنتَج كبير من القشرة الدماغية.
Only the wealth of our minds is,
فقط هي ثروة عقولنا,
not the very fact that we have a self
وليست فكرة ان لدينا نفس
that we can refer
بامكاننا ان نشير
to our own existence,
الى وجودنا نفسه,
and that we have any sense of person.
و ان لدينا اي شعور كاشخاص.
Now there are three levels of self to consider --
الآن هناك ثلاثة مستويات للنظر في النفس --
the proto, the core and the autobiographical.
الذهن الحدسي, الذهن الواقعي ، الذهن المبرمج
The first two are shared
الاثنين الاوائل مشتركة
with many, many other species,
مع الكثير, الكثير من الاصناف الاخرى,
and they are really coming out
وهي في الواقع تخرج
largely of the brain stem
إلى حد كبير من جذع الدماغ
and whatever there is of cortex in those species.
وايا كان هناك من القشرة في تلك الاصناف.
It's the autobiographical self
هو الذهن المبرمج
which some species have, I think.
الذي لدى بعض الاصناف, على ما اعتقد.
Cetaceans and primates have also
الحيتان والثدييات أيضا لها
an autobiographical self to a certain degree.
الذهن المبرمج الى حد ما.
And everybody's dogs at home
وكل الكلاب الموجوده في المنزل
have an autobiographical self to a certain degree.
لديها الذهن المبرمج الى حد ما.
But the novelty is here.
ولكن الجديد يقع هنا.
The autobiographical self is built
تتكون الذهن المبرمج
on the basis of past memories
على اساس ذكريات الماضي
and memories of the plans that we have made;
وذكريات الخطط التي صنعناها
it's the lived past and the anticipated future.
هي الماضي الذي عشناه و المستقبل المتوقع.
And the autobiographical self
و الذهن المبرمج
has prompted extended memory, reasoning,
دفعت الى توسيع الذاكرة و المنطق,
imagination, creativity and language.
والخيال والابداع واللغة.
And out of that came the instruments of culture --
والتي جائت بادوات الثقافة ---
religions, justice,
الاديان والعدل,
trade, the arts, science, technology.
والفنون والعلوم والتكنولوجيا.
And it is within that culture
وفي مضمون تلك الثقافة
that we really can get --
انه حقيقة بامكاننا الحصول على--
and this is the novelty --
وهذه هي الحداثة --
something that is not entirely set by our biology.
شيئ لم يثبت كاملا من خلال ﺍﻟﺒﻴﻭﻟﻭﺠﻴﺎ لدينا
It is developed in the cultures.
هي طُورت في الثقافات
It developed in collectives of human beings.
تطورت في تجمعات من البشر.
And this is, of course, the culture
وهذه, طبعا, هي الثقافة
where we have developed something that I like to call
ولقد طورنا شيئ احب ان اسميه
socio-cultural regulation.
التنظيم الاجتماعي الثقافي.
And finally, you could rightly ask,
واخيرا, بامكانكم ان تسألوا,
why care about this?
لماذا نهتم بذلك؟
Why care if it is the brain stem or the cerebral cortex
لماذا نهتم اذا ما كانت هي جذع الدماغ أو القشرة الدماغية
and how this is made?
وكيف تتكون؟
Three reasons. First, curiosity.
لثلاثة اسباب. الاول, الفضول
Primates are extremely curious --
الثديات فضولية للغاية --
and humans most of all.
والانسان اكثرها.
And if we are interested, for example,
واذا كنا مهتمون, على سبيل المثال,
in the fact that anti-gravity
في حقيقة ان المضاد للجاذبية
is pulling galaxies away from the Earth,
يسحب المجرات بعيدا عن الارض,
why should we not be interested in what is going on
فلما لا نهتم بما يدور
inside of human beings?
داخل الانسان؟
Second, understanding society and culture.
ثانيا, فهم المجتمع و الثفافة
We should look
يجب أن ننظر
at how society and culture
الى كيف ان المجتمع و الثقافة
in this socio-cultural regulation
في هذا النظام الاجتماعي الثقافي
are a work in progress.
انه عمل في تقدم.
And finally, medicine.
واخيرا, الطب.
Let's not forget that some of the worst diseases
دعونا لا ننسى ان بعض من اسوأ الامراض
of humankind
البشرية
are diseases such as depression,
هي أمراض مثل الاكتئاب،
Alzheimer's disease, drug addiction.
ومرض الزهايمر وإدمان المخدرات.
Think of strokes that can devastate your mind
فكر في السكتات الدماغية التي بامكانها تدمير الدماغ
or render you unconscious.
او تتسبب في فقدانك الوعي
You have no prayer
ليس لديك دعاء
of treating those diseases effectively
لعلاج هذه الامراض بشكل فعال
and in a non-serendipitous way
ولا عن طريق الصدفة
if you do not know how this works.
اذا لم تدري طريقة عملها.
So that's a very good reason
لذلك فهذا سبب وجيه جدا
beyond curiosity
يتجاوز الفضول
to justify what we're doing,
لتبرير ما نقوم به،
and to justify having some interest in what is going on in our brains.
وتبرير اهتمامنا بما يجري داخل الدماغ.
Thank you for your attention.
شكرا على حسن استماعكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)